A Guide to the Papers of Charles Snowden Fairfax, 1850-1913
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Charles Snowden Fairfax 1850-1913
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7041
This collection consists of seventeen items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collecton was placed on loan in the Library on March 19, 1963, and was made a gift by Mrs. C. Marshall Barton, Jr., of Owings Mills, Maryland, on December 3, 1980.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of seventeen items, 1850-1913, relating to Charles Snowden Fairfax (1829-1869), of Virginia and California. Included in the collection are eleven letters, 1850-1861, written by Fairfax to: his mother, Caroline E. Sanders; his brother, John C. Fairfax; Charles S. Coutel; and Nicholas Shipley. The letters describe Fairfax's life in California during the gold rush and include accounts of the economic situation, gold mining, the landscape, his farm, and living conditions. Also present is a letter from Fairfax's uncle, Richard Snowden, to Caroline E. Sanders, describing his and Charles's work in the mines. Copies of two accounts of Charles Fairfax's death appearing in the Baltimore Sun, April 5, 1869, a 1913 newspaper clipping from the San Francisco Bulletin regarding Charles Fairfax and his wife; and two photographs of Charles Fairfax and his wife complete the collection.
Charles Snowden Fairfax was born at "Vancluse," Fairfax County, Virginia, on March 8, 1829, the son of Albert Fairfax of Virginia and Caroline Eliza Snowden of Maryland. He became de jure 10th Lord Fairfax of Cameron in 1846 upon the death of his grandfather, Thomas Fairfax ( de jure 9th baron) of "Vaucluse," Fairfax County, Virginia (Albert Fairfax having predeceased his father in 1835). Charles married Ada Benham of Cincinnati, Ohio, and was a pioneer settler in California. He was elected to the first House of Delegates when that state was admitted to the Union and became speaker of the house in 1854. In 1857 he became clerk of the Supreme Court of California and served in that position for five years. Fairfax died in Baltimore, Maryland, on April 4, 1869.
Contents List
- Charles Fairfax, Panama, to Charles S. Coutel, Prince Georges Co., Maryland 1850 May 27, 2 pp.
- Charles Fairfax, San Francisco, to John C. Fairfax, Washington City, D. C. 1850 Jun 22, 3 pp.
- Charles Fairfax, San Francisco, to Mrs. Caroline E. Sanders, Washington City, D.C. 1850 Jun 23, 3 pp.
- Charles Fairfax, San Francisco, to Mrs. Caroline E. Sanders, Washington City, D.C. 1850 Jun 26, 3 pp.
- Charles Fairfax, Feather River, to Nicholas H. Shipley, Prince George Co., Maryland 1850 Jun 28, 2 pp.
- Charles Fairfax, Nevada City, Sierra [?], Nevada to Nicholas Shipley, Prince Georges Co., Maryland 1850 Jul 20, 3 pp.
- Charles Fairfax, California Northern Mines, to [?] 1850 Oct 3, 4 pp.
- Richard Snowden, Feather River, to Mrs. Caroline E. Sanders, Washington, D.C. 1850 Oct 25, 3 pp.
- Charles Fairfax, Assembly Chamber, to [Caroline E. Sanders] 1853 May 8, 4 pp.
- Charles Fairfax, Sacramento City, to Mrs. Caroline E. Sanders, Woodburne 1857 Jul 3, 4 pp.
- [Charles Fairfax] to [Caroline E. Sanders] 1858 Jul 19, 4 pp.
- Charles Fairfax, San Rafael, Marin County, California, to [Caroline E. Sanders] 1861 Jun 9, 2 pp.
- Notarized copies of accounts of Charles Snowden Fairfax's death appearing in the Baltimore Sun, April 5, 1869 1900 Dec 26, 2 pp.
- "Stories of Charles Fairfax and His Wife, and Their 'Open House', Near Sun Rafael" 1913 Jan 25, 2 pp.
- Mrs. Charles Fairfax n.d., Photograph
- Charles Fairfax n.d., Photograph